No!
There she is. There she is.
There she is.
Ladies and gentlemen,
I've traveled over half our state to be here tonight.
I couldn't get away sooner because my new well was coming in
at Coyote Hills and I had to see about it.
That well is now flowing at 2,000 barrels
and it's paying me an income of $5,000 a week.
I have two others drilling and I have 16 producing at Antelope,
so, ladies and gentlemen, if I say I'm an oilman, you will agree.
Now, you have a great chance here,
but bear in mind you could lose it all if you're not careful.
Out of all men that beg for a chance to drill your lots,
maybe one in twenty will be oilmen.
The rest will be speculators,
that's men trying to get between you and the oilmen
to get some of the money that ought, by rights, come to you.
Even if you find one that has money and means to drill,
he'll maybe know nothing about drilling.
He'll have to hire the job out on contract,
and then you're depending on a contractor,
who'll rush the job through
so he can get another contract just as quick as he can.
This is the way that this works.
What is your offer? We're wasting time.
Please!
I do my own drilling.
And the men that work for me, work for me, and they are men I know.
I make it my business to be there and to see their work.
I don't lose my tools in the hole and spend months fishing for them.
I don't botch the cementing off
and let water in the hole and ruin the whole lease.
I'm a family man.
I run a family business. This is my son and my partner, H.W. Plainview.
We offer you the bond of family that very few oilmen can understand.
I'm fixed like no other company in this field
and that's because my Coyote Hills well has just come in.
I have a string of tools all ready to put to work.
I can load a rig onto trucks and have them here in a week.
I have business connections, so I can get the lumber for the derricks.
Such things go by friendship in a rush like this.
And this is why I can guarantee to start drilling
and to put up the cash to back my word.
I assure you, ladies and gentlemen,
no matter what the others promise to do,
when it comes to the showdown, they won't be there.
Sit down! Sit down, you have no right...
Let us discuss what the man has to say.
- Prescott, do you trust this man? - Let's discuss what he has to say.
- There's logic to what he's saying. - How does he know? My lot is there!
Two or three years, it could be ten years!
- We gain nothing by losing our heads! - Look at that well out there!
Nobody's losing their heads.
You have no business being here!
Sit that woman down, sir!
You can sit down.
Mr. Plainview! Please, Mr. Plainview.
No, Mr. Plainview! No, where are you going?
- I don't need the lease. Thank you. - But we need you.
Too much confusion. Thank you for your time.
No, no, there's no confusion.
I wouldn't take the lease if you gave it to me as a gift.
Mr. Bankside, I'm not going to waste your time.
I'd certainly appreciate it if you didn't waste mine.
Now, if you wish to sign with me, we can have a well drilling within 10 days.
Your lot is further north from the discovery well up here.
That means we'll probably have to dig deeper.
And if there's as much oil here as I think there is,
it'll be harder to reach, but once we find it, we can take it right out.
We have to act quickly, because very soon these fields will be dry.
I need you to know what you want to do.
Now, because of the distance from the discovery well,
I'll pay you a smaller royalty than you'd get down there
but I'm prepared to give you a $1,000 bonus on your lot.
What kind of royalty are you talking about?
One-sixth, plus a guarantee to start drilling within 10 days.
Now, that's something you won't find anywhere else.
What age are your children, ma'am?
Ten and twelve.
Mr. Plainview, a question, sir. Where is your wife?
She died in childbirth, Mrs. Bankside.
So it's just me and my son now.
It's coming in, boss!
Hear it?
Mr. Plainview?
Yes?
Are you Daniel Plainview?
Yes.
What can I do for you?
You look for oil.
That's right.
What do you pay for a place that has it?
- Well, that depends. - What does it depend on?
On a lot of things.
If I told you I knew a place that had oil where land could be bought cheaply,
what do you think that would be worth?
I think that you should let me know what you know
and then we'll try and work something out.
- Can I sit down? - Please.
What church do you belong to?
I...
I enjoy all faiths. I don't belong to one church in particular.
I like them all. I like everything. Where are you from?
That would be telling you. That's what I want to sell you.
What are you doing in Signal Hill?
We have oil, and it seeps through the ground.
Do you want to pay me to know where it is?
Just 'cause there's something on the ground
doesn't mean there's anything beneath it.
Why did Standard Oil buy up land?
Is it in California?
- Maybe. - How much land did they buy?
I'd like it better if you didn't think I was stupid.
Why did you come to me?
- You just brought this well in. - That's right.
Yes, so just give me $500 in cash right now
and I'll tell you where it is.
I'll tell you what I'll do, son. I'll give you $100 now,
and if it proves to be a promising lease, then give you a $1,000 bonus.
Six hundred dollars.
Tell me one thing to help me decide. What else have you got up there?
What do you grow?
We have a big ranch, but it's mostly rocks.
Plant things. Nothing will grow but weeds.
What makes you think it's up?
Is there sulfur around? Or alkali deposits?
Alkali nearby. I don't know sulfur.
Is that your son?
Yes.
- Hi. - Hi.
- Who are you? - I'm Fletcher Hamilton.
Nice to meet you, son. What's your name?
What do you do?
I work with Mr. Plainview.
Here's $500, son.
You tell me something worth hearing, this money's yours.
I come from a town called Little Boston in Isabella County.
This is us, here. Spur station here at Little Boston.
The Sunday ranch is what you're looking for.
There's a sheep trail that takes you there.
It's a mile out of town headed west, not far.
Just through a small pass here near the base of the hills.
You'll pass a church and just follow the sheep trail.
- Where's Standard buying up? - Here and here.
- Your family name is Sunday, yes? - That's right.
How many's in your family?
My father and mother and sisters and my brother Eli.
- How many sisters do you have? - Two.
- What's your name? - Paul.
Does any of your family know about the oil that you say is there?
I don't know.
My uncle always said there was oil there,
but I don't know what they heard or what they think.
What do you grow?
lt's goats. It's a goat farm. I told you, nothing grows but weeds.
- Is there water? - It's salty.
You drill a well, it's hard not to get saltwater.
The oil is there. I'm telling you.
- I want to go now, so... - You can stay tonight.
- No, I want to go now. I want to leave. - Listen, Paul.
If I travel all the way out there and I find that you've been lying to me,
I'm going to find you and I'm going to take more than my money back.
Is that all right with you?
- Yes, sir. - All right, then.
- Nice luck to you. God bless. - And to you, young man.
- There's someone coming. - Thank you, Mary.
- Good evening. - Good evening.
My name's Daniel Plainview. This is my son, H.W.
- Are you hunting? - Hunting for quail.
We're told there might be a good place to camp up near the Sunday ranch.
This is the Sunday ranch. You can camp here.
- Thank you. Do you have water? - Yes.
We heard there was an earthquake up here a few days ago.
- Is that right? - Yes.
- Your family? - Yeah, all fine. Thank you.
- We have goat's milk, if you'd like. - That would be fine.
Now,
if we set our tent away over there, we'd be out of your way over there.
That's fine.
Ruth! Help these men and bring them some water.
No! H.W.
Mr. Plainview, would you like that milk now?
- That would be fine. Thank you. - Mary! Bring them some milk.
My family will help you set up your tent.
No, please. We set ourselves on this camping trip.
We have to do the camping.
Hurry up!
- Do you have bread? - We have potatoes.
Potatoes would be nice, thank you.
I'll have them boil you up some potatoes.
That's all right. I thought maybe we'd make a fire.
I wanted to work with my son on making a fire.
All right. My son, Eli, will bring you some wood.
Thank you so much for your hospitality, Mr. Sunday.
- Yes. - And we'll be out of your way.
- We're just hunting for quail. - Yes.
- I'm sorry we don't have any bread. - No, no, no.
Corn doesn't fill out in the hills here. It's mostly rock.
We don't have room to raise the grain.
Thank you, young lady.
My name is Eli.
Yes, you're Eli Sunday.
Welcome.
- H.W. - Eli.
- You're hunting quail? - That's right.
- We will bring dinner. - Thank you. Thank you so much.
Dad!
Dad, look at my shoe.
That's earthquake oil. Set loose.
So...
So?
So, so.
If there's anything here, we take it to the sea.
What we do is we build a pipeline to Port Hueneme or Santa Paula,
it's about 100 miles,
and we do a deal with Union Oil. This is what we do.
Then we don't need the railroads and their shipping costs anymore.
You see?
Yeah.
- You see that? - Yeah.
Then we're making money. We're making the real money.
What we should be making. Not just...
Not just throwing it away on shipping costs.
Otherwise, it's just mud.
How much are we going to pay them?
Who's that?
The Sunday family.
I'm not going to give them oil prices.
I'll give them quail prices.
If we could take a few minutes,
there's something I'd very much like to talk with you about.
Mother, would you take the girls outside, please?
I believe in plain speaking, so...
This is a beautiful ranch. I love hunting for quail.
My boy has been sick, you know. He needs fresh air.
Doctors all say he needs plentiful fresh air.
So,
what would you say would be a fair price for this lot, Abel?
- To buy this place? - That's right.
Take a moment.
- I'm sorry. I don't know. - Six dollars an acre.
Six dollars? Thank you, Eli.
And then with the improvements to the ranch over the years at $500...
I'd like to offer you $3,700 for this ranch.
- That's $3,700. - No.
The Lord has sent this man here, Eli.
Yes, I believe He has.
- My offer to you is $3,700. - What is it that brought you here, sir?
The Good Lord's guidance.
- Now, of course, within that... - What about our oil?
...we're going to develop a lease.
- What's that? - What about our oil?
What about it?
We have oil here. That's worth something.
Do you have someone who can drill for it?
- Do you think there's oil here? - I know there is.
It's very expensive to drill.
To get it up and out of the ground. You ever tried that before?
- How much is it? - Costly.
Well, our oil sits right up on top of the ground.
I believe that's called seepage.
Doesn't necessarily mean there's anything underneath.
- What would you give us for it? - I don't know.
- Something you don't know. - That's right.
What would you like, Eli?
Ten thousand dollars.
For what?
For my church.
That's good.
That's a good one.
Well...
If we decide to drill for oil and if the well begins to produce,
I'll give your church a $5,000 signing bonus.
Ten thousand.
Do you want to find someone else that's going to come here and drill, Eli?
Make the investment and do all the hard work that goes into it?
I can just as easily hunt for quail on another ranch as I can here, so...
Though I'll happily be a supporter of your church for as long as I can.
For the bonus only.
Now, as it happens, I do have some connections in the drilling business
who might help get us started. How do you feel about this, Abel?
Yes. What Eli says.
Well, good! Let's draw up some contracts and let's...
Let's give it a try.
Appreciate your help with this, Eli.
- Good afternoon. - Good afternoon.
- Real estate? - Yes.
Yes, I'd like to talk to you.
I'm looking for some land. I just bought the Sunday ranch.
And, well, where's the map?
Where are the hills behind the Sunday ranch?
That's here. It's the Bandy tract. He has over 600 acres.
Bandy, 600.
- What about this? - A.C. Maude, Blodget, Redlick, Carr.
- What's it held at? - Six dollars an acre.
Six.
What about this?
That's the Belvins, and that could be got, I'm sure.
Can everything around here be got?
Sure.
Paul Sunday turned out to be a good friend of ours.
That's right.
Well, you get here just as soon as you can. Bring Fred English.
Good enough.
Thank you, porter.
- H.W., how are you? - Fine, and you?
- Pretty good. Where's your dad? - He's inside.
You fellas are a long way from Signal Hill.
- Hello, Plainview. - Hello, Gene.
- Good to see you. - Charlie.
- On your way somewhere else? - Passing through. Looking around.
- Funny to see you. - Funny, isn't it?
You boys are a regular family business.
You boys are a little late.
- What did you find? - I found some interesting prospects.
Did you hear Standard bought up?
- Mostly in the north, so far. - That's what I hear.
I'm gonna tell you, Gene, if you're gonna make a play, look east.
I'd rather it be you than someone else. This mud around here has been taken.
It must be easy when you have such a cute face to carry around with you.
- Telling me how handsome my son is? - Well, that I am.
That's very nice. Thank you. Good luck, Gene.
- Take care. - Like I said, go east.
H.W.
I'll be your lawyer if you need to draw up a contract.
Make sure you don't get swindled, boy. Get half what your dad's making.
How's that?
What are those men doing?
They're just guys that are working for us.
They're just looking around.
How much money can we make?
I don't know. It depends.
One thousand dollars?
Mary said that her father beats her if she doesn't pray.
Mary, she's the smaller one?
Yes, she is.
- Everyone here? - Very successful.
But?
There were a few vacant lots and one holdout.
- Who? - William Bandy.
...eight. Who's he?
He's an old man who homesteaded here.
Lives with his grandson. He said he'd like to speak with you.
Is he here?
No, he'd like you to come visit with him.
He's boosting his price.
He said he'd like to speak with whoever is doing the buying.
Well, let him wait. He'll come around. Let's go.
Ladies and gentlemen?
Ladies and gentlemen.
Thank you so much for visiting with us this evening.
Now, I've traveled across half our state to be here and to see about this land.
Now, I daresay some of you might have heard
some of the more extravagant rumors about what my plans are,
so I just thought you'd like to hear it from me.
This is the face. It's no great mystery.
I'm an oilman, ladies and gentlemen,
I have numerous concerns spread across this state.
I have many wells flowing at many thousand barrels per day,
so I like to think of myself as an oilman.
As an oilman, I hope that you'll forgive
just good old-fashioned plain speaking.
Now, this work that we do is very much a family enterprise.
I work side by side with my wonderful son, H. W.
I think one or two of you might have met him already.
And I encourage my men to bring their families, as well.
Of course, it makes for an ever so much more rewarding life for them.
Family means children, and children means education.
So, wherever we set up camp, education is a necessity,
and we're just so happy to take care of that.
So let's build a wonderful school in Little Boston.
These children are the future that we strive for,
and so they should have the very best of things.
Now, something else,
and please don't be insulted if I speak about this. Bread.
Let's talk about bread.
Now, to my mind, it's an abomination to consider
that any man, woman, or child in this magnificent country of ours
should have to look upon a loaf of bread as a luxury.
We're going to dig water wells here, and water wells means irrigation.
Irrigation means cultivation.
We're going to raise crops here where before it just simply wasn't possible.
You're going to have more grain than you'll know what to do with,
and bread will be coming right out of your ears, ma'am.
New roads, agriculture, employment, education.
These are just a few of the things we can offer you,
and I assure you, ladies and gentlemen,
that if we do find oil here,
and I think there's a very good chance that we will,
this community of yours will not only survive, it will flourish.
I'd be happy to answer any questions that you might have. Yes?
Will the new road lead to the church?
That'll be the first place that it leads. Thank you, Eli. Anyone else?
Well, if anything comes up, I'm pretty easy to find.
You just come visit with me.
Thank you so much for your time, and good night.
What a privilege to carry
everything to God in prayer!
What a privilege to carry...
Just follow the new road right to the church.
The new road will lead you there.
Hello, brother, my name is Eli.
The Church of the Third Revelation welcomes you.
Just follow the new road right to the church.
Jesus knows our every weakness
Take it to the Lord in prayer
Are we weak and heavy-laden
Cumbered with a load of care?
Precious Savior still our refuge
Take it to the Lord in prayer...
- Daniel, may I speak with you? - Yes, come in.
I'll bring them up when they arrive.
- Good morning. - Good morning.
How is all the work coming?
Everything's good.
- All the men are provided for? - Of course.
Spirits seem high.
Is there anything that you need from me?
- Anything the church can do for you? - I don't believe so. No. Thank you.
I understand you've asked the people to gather around
and watch the well begin tomorrow. Is that right?
- That's right. - I will bless the well.
Before you begin, you should introduce me.
You'll see me walk up towards the oil well, and when I...
The derrick.
You'll see me walk up, and then you could say my name.
When you walk up?
Yes. You'll see me walk up, and then you could say,
"The proud son of these hills who tended his Father's flock,"
and then you could say my name.
That's fine.
- And what happens then? - Well, then we start the drill.
It's a simple blessing, Daniel, but an important one.
It's just a few words. It won't take long.
- What time? - What time's good for you, Eli?
- 4:00. - Well, let's make it 4:00 then.
- My thanks for your visit. - Good day. Thank you.
Afternoon, everyone.
Come with me.
I thank you all so much for visiting with us at this time.
I've had the pleasure of meeting some of you
and I hope very much in the months to come,
I'll be able to visit with each and every one of you.
I'm better at digging holes in the ground than making speeches,
so let's forget the speech for this evening,
just make it a simple blessing.
You see, one man doesn't prospect from the ground.
It takes a whole community of good people, such as yourselves,
and this is good. We stay together.
We pray together, we work together,
and if the Good Lord smiles kindly on our endeavor,
we share in the wealth together.
Now, before we spud in Mary's Well Number One,
named for the lovely Miss Mary Sunday, here by my side,
a proud daughter of these hills,
I'd just like to say God bless these honest labors of ours, and, of course,
God bless you all.
Amen.
Now go.
Won't be a minute.
Fast as you can, H.W.
Are you ready to do this?
That's it, ladies and gentlemen!
Al Rose has very generously provided some refreshments for this occasion
out of his own pocket. Thank you, Al.
If you'll all just care to help yourselves, I'll be back in a minute.
Mary.
Mary Sunday.
- Do you like your new dress? - Yes. Thank you.
You're welcome. I thought you'd like it.
- Are you happy I came here? - Yes.
Your daddy doesn't hit you anymore, does he? Does he now?
Better not, right?
I'll take care of you.
No more hitting, right? No more hitting. Now go.
Go and play some more and don't come back.
Daniel?
lt's okay, H.W. Go back to sleep. Go on. Go back to sleep.
Daniel.
Daniel!
What?
Lost a man down the well.
- What man? - Joe Gundha.
- Did I know him? - No.
What happened?
Pick it up.
Set the brake.
- Tie it down. - Tie it on.
Shit!
God damn it. Where's the body?
- They're fishing it out now. - All right.
- Where's the bit? - It's on the deck.
Clean him up. Put some clothes on him.
And...
Set up a tent.
Anyone goes down into the cellar, you tell somebody. Yes?
- Yes, sir. - Yes, sir.
Shut down till midday.
And I had a vision. Yes, last night, I had a vision
and I felt God's breath move through me.
And it rolled down into my stomach.
It sloshed around.
And my stomach spoke in a whisper, not a shout,
"Touch this woman with your hands and caress her." Yes.
My dear Mrs. Hunter,
you have arthritis, don't you?
- Yes, I do, Eli. - Yes.
The devil is in your hands, and I will suck it out.
Now, I will not cast this ghost out with a fever
for the new spirit inside me has shown me I have a new way to communicate.
It is a gentle whisper.
Get out of here, ghost.
Get out.
...and enter this woman's body now. - Get out of here, ghost.
Get out of here. Don't you dare turn around and come back.
For if you do,
all the armies of my boot will kick you in the teeth
and you will be cast up and thrown in the dirt
and thrust back to perdition!
And as long as I have teeth, I will bite you,
and if I have no teeth, I will gum you!
And as long as I have fists, I will bash you!
Now, get out of here, ghost! Get out of here, ghost!
Get out of here, ghost!
And it left!
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
- Praise the Lord and his holy days! - Praise God!
- Amen! Thank you. - Thank you, Jesus. Thank you, God.
My dear Mrs. Hunter.
Dance with me.
- Thanks for coming. - It was a wonderful sermon.
- Will I see you tomorrow? - Yes.
Eli.
Had a tragedy at the well last night.
Yes, I heard.
Joe Gundha was a man of considerable faith.
So if you wish to say a few words, his burial is at noon tomorrow.
Daniel, this accident could have been avoided.
It is terrible to think of that well
- working away out there... - These men work in 12-hour shifts.
...unblessed. - They need their rest.
If they don't have it, they start to make stupid mistakes.
I've seen the men drinking. Don't you think that has something to do with this?
We need these men well-rested to bring in this well.
They can't get that if they're up here listening to your gospel,
and then the well can't produce and blow gold all over the place.
I wish I had more time with Joe Gundha.
More could have been done.
Then the well can't produce and blow gold all over the place.
Now, would you see to it that his personal possessions
find their way back to his family, please?
Thank you.
Heard you were planning some renovations.
Yes, our congregation is growing strongly.
- We need more room. - That was one goddamn hell of a show.
We were happy to have you, Daniel.
Gas, gas, gas!
Lights out! Wait here. Wait here. Lights out!
Put that fire out!
Is he hurt? H.W.! Hand him down to me!
- Hand him down! - Here.
- Got him? - I've got him!
Oh, God.
Come on.
Open the door.
Let go. There you go. You're safe. You're safe.
You're safe now. I got you here. You're safe. Let go, son.
Tell me where it hurts. Tell me where it hurts. Tell me where...
- Did you see this? - No.
Tell me where it hurts.
Where does it hurt you? Where does it hurt you?
- I can't hear my voice. - Were you hit in the head?
Were you hit in the head? Tell me! You have to tell me if you were!
I can't hear my voice.
I have to go and deal with this now. You wait here for me.
You understand? You wait here for me. I'll be back. I'll be back in a minute.
- Wait here. - Don't leave!
I'm going to take care of you. Wait. Stay here, son. I'm going to fix this.
- Don't leave! - You're going to be fine!
Wait for me here!
- Hold him down. Hold him down. - Don't leave!
Got to break the cables, Daniel!
Get me a hammer!
Here you go.
Get back!
- Michael! - Sir!
Take Dave and two of the fellas, pick up some hoses...
Billy, protect the roof. Don't wait before it gets too hot.
What are you looking so miserable about?
There's a whole ocean of oil under our feet!
No one can get at it except for me.
H.W. okay?
No, he isn't.
- Where is he? - Mess room.
That's enough now. That's enough, H.W. That's enough.
Do you hear me? Can you hear me in there?
That's enough.
- Grab his legs. - I have his legs.
- No. Nope. - No, lad.
Give me that.
Steady. That's it.
- Easy, boy. Easy. - Soon be over.
Yeah, and that's good. Now the other side. Turn him over.
Almost done.
That's it.
Come here. It's over. It's over.
Who do we know in San Francisco
or Los Angeles, who could work with...
You know, we could... Someone, a teacher for H.W.
How could you figure out that?
Now, call... God damn it, what's his name?
Bob Brody in San Francisco?
Call Bob Brody and get someone down here.
I'll do it right away.
When do we get our money, Daniel?
Aren't you a healer? And a vessel for the Holy Spirit?
When are you coming over and make my son hear again?
Can't you do that?
lf you had let me bless the well, this wouldn't have happened.
- Daniel. - You shouldn't have done that.
You owe the Church of the Third Revelation $5,000
as part of the arrangement that we made!
Don't even try it, you little runt! You splash around in here.
That's it, that's it.
I'm going to bury you underground, Eli.
I'm going to bury you underground.
You are a stupid man, Abel.
You've let someone come in here and walk all over us.
You let him in and do his work here,
and you are a stupid man for what we could have had.
I followed His word, Eli. I tried.
You didn't do anything but sit down.
You're lazy, and you're stupid.
Do you think God is going to save you for being stupid?
He doesn't save stupid people, Abel.
I will tear you apart for what you've done, you stupid man!
How did he come here? Do you really know? I know!
- Son, don't do this, please! - Be quiet!
Shut your mouth, Abel! lt was your stupid son!
lt was Paul who told him to come here. I know it.
He went to him and he said,
"My stupid, weak father will give away his lots.
"Go and take him." And you let it happen.
A stupid father to a stupid son.
Get out of there!
Can I help you?
Daniel?
- Who's that? - My name is Henry.
Yeah?
I'm Henry.
What can I do for you?
I'm Henry Plainview. I'm from Fond du Lac.
I'm your brother, from another mother.
Ernest is my father.
Who are you?
Henry.
- Mary Branch? Is that your mother? - Yes, sir, that's right.
I read about your gusher in the paper, about your success.
You heard about my strike? You just show up?
Our father's dead.
Ernest died, I heard. I wanted to find you.
When?
Three months ago. I got a letter from Annabelle.
My sister, Annabelle?
- Where is she? - Still at home. Fond du Lac.
You came all the way from Wisconsin to tell me this?
I'm coming from New Mexico. I've been there.
I came to find you.
Did you know about me?
Do you have identification?
Do you have this letter?
- Where are you coming from? - From New Mexico.
Yes, I know, but from where?
Silver City. I've been there for two years.
I was trying drilling of my own for years.
- Getting leases in Texas. Louisiana. - Anything that produced?
No. Not like your success, no.
- Are you married? - No.
I spent time in jail. I had a stretch of very bad time.
I had nothing. I was picked up in Louisiana.
I worked on a chain gang for six months building roads.
That was a very hard time.
Are you married?
What were you in jail for?
Believe it or not, for all the terrible things I've gotten myself into,
when they picked me up, I hadn't done anything.
But I've done my share of things
that shouldn't be talked about.
Drink it. Drink it!
Come on.
So...
What do you want, Henry?
Nothing.
If you can spare something, I can work for you in any way.
I know I'll keep moving, before long, to get back to Fond du Lac.
- Do you have any money? - Some.
- Not much. - Just answer me directly.
You say "nothing," then you say you'd like to stay and work.
And it's better, I'd just like to hear you say you'd like to be here.
I'd like to be here.
I'm a good worker. I worked cable tool rigs, built railroads.
I won't need any favors.
Good.
What did my mother know?
I don't know.
I don't know if she knew and looked the other way, if she never knew.
Why did you leave?
I know you didn't get on with our father.
I worked for Geological Survey and went to Kansas.
I couldn't stay there. I just couldn't.
I don't like to explain myself.
- Are you an angry man, Henry? - About what?
Are you envious? Do you get envious?
I don't think so, no.
I have a competition in me.
I want no one else to succeed.
- I hate most people. - That part of me is gone.
Working and not succeeding,
all my failures have left me...
I just don't care.
Well, if it's in me, it's in you.
There are times when I look at people and I see nothing worth liking.
I want to earn enough money I can get away from everyone.
What will you do about your boy?
I don't know.
Maybe it'll change.
Does your sound come back to you? I don't know. Maybe no one knows that.
- Doctor might not know that. - Where's his mother?
I don't want to talk about those things.
I see the worst in people, Henry.
I don't need to look past seeing them to get all I need.
I've built up my hatreds over the years, little by little.
Having you here gives me a second breath of life.
I can't keep doing this on my own
with these people.
Daniel! Daniel, wake up! Daniel!
Just have to go and have a word with the conductor.
I'll be right back.
You stay here. You understand? You stay here.
No! No!
No!
- Tilford! - Plainview.
This is my brother, Henry Plainview from Fond du Lac.
H.M. Tilford. Pleasure.
Henry Plainview. J.J. Carter.
So...
- Shall we? - Yes.
How's your boy?
- Thank you for asking. - Is there anything we can do?
Thanks for asking is enough.
So what are your plans?
Is this about buying up my tracts here?
Yes.
The cable was about my Coyote Hills lease.
- We'd like that, too. - What's your offer on Coyote Hills?
- We'll offer 150,000 for full title. - That's a deal. What's next?
You have 11,000 acres in Little Boston. You have one proven well
- that was damaged... - I have three wells proven.
You haven't been paying attention. That's three proven wells.
We'll make you a millionaire while you're sitting here
from one minute to the next.
And what else would I do with myself?
- Are you asking me? - What else would I do with myself?
Take care of your son.
I don't know what you would do.
If you were me and Standard offered to buy what you had
for a million dollars, why? So, why?
You know why.
Yeah, you fellas should just scratch around in the dirt
and find it like the rest of us, instead of buying up someone else's hard work.
I've scratched around the dirt, son.
You going to change your shipping costs?
We don't dictate shipping costs. That's railroad business.
You don't own the railroads?
'Course you do. Of course you do.
Where you going to put it all?
Where?
Build a pipeline? Make a deal with Union Oil? Be my guest.
But if you can't pull it off,
you've got an ocean of oil under your feet with nowhere to go.
Why not turn it over to us? We'll make you rich.
You spend time with your boy.
It's a great discovery.
Now, let us help you.
Did you just tell me how to run my family?
lt might be more important now that you've proven the field
and we're offering to buy you out.
One night I'm going to come to you, inside of your house,
or wherever you're sleeping, and I'm going to cut your throat.
What?
What are you talking about? Have you gone crazy?
- Did you hear what I said? - I heard what you said,
- why did you say it? - You don't tell me about my son.
Why are you acting insane and threatening to cut my throat?
- You don't tell me about my son. - I'm not telling you anything!
I'm asking you to be reasonable. If I've offended you, I apologize.
You'll see what I can do.
This parcel here is the 3,000-acre ranch owned by B.L. Harper.
This is San Luis Obispo County land.
And from here to the coast, it's all Union Oil.
What's this? Why don't I own this?
- Why don't I own this? - That's the Bandy tract.
He was the holdout, when we were doing the buying.
He had hoped to speak with you.
Can't you just build the pipeline around this tract?
Can I build around 50 miles of Tehachapi mountains?
Don't be thick in front of me, Al.
- I can go to him again. - No, I'll go and talk to the man.
I'll talk to him. Show you how it's done.
All right. Pack it up, Henry.
- How big is his room? - He's sharing with another boy.
- Who? - An older boy. About 12.
He's been there for a year. Named Ballard.
- How big is the room? - It's a fair size. Got enough space.
Are you taking Henry with you to meet Union Oil?
- Are you the son of William Bandy? - Grandson.
- Is he here? - No, he's out.
Where is he?
Told you, he's out. Now, what do you want?
I'm Daniel Plainview. I want to talk with him about his property.
- About what? - I believe I'll talk with him about that.
- You're that oilman, aren't you? - That's right.
We don't want you drilling out here.
I don't want it either. Now, when will he be back?
Few days.
Tell him I'd like to speak with him. Not about drilling.
And I'll be back in a week.
Put that in a glass case.
Here's to Union Oil.
Hundred miles of pipeline,
and all the independent producers of this great state.
Cheers.
There's that house in Fond du Lac
that John Hollister built. Do you remember it?
I thought as a boy that was the most beautiful house I'd ever seen,
and I wanted it.
I wanted to live in it.
And eat in it.
And clean it.
And even as a boy, I wanted to have children to run around in it.
You can have anything you'd like now, Daniel.
And you should.
- Where are you going to build it? - Here, maybe. Near the ocean.
Would you make it look like that house?
I think if I saw that house now, it'd make me sick.
We can eat and get some women.
Take them to the Peachtree dance.
I say get liquored up and take them to the Peachtree dance.
Yeah.
Can I have some money, please?
I want you to tell me something.
What?
What's the name of the farm next to the Hill House?
What was the name of the farm next to the Hill House?
- I can't remember... - Who are you?
I'll leave, Daniel.
Who are you?
I'm no one.
Just let me get up and go.
Do I have a brother?
I met a man in King City who said he was your brother.
We were friends for months.
Working in King City.
And he wanted to make his way to you, Daniel.
We didn't have any money.
He died of tuberculosis.
He wasn't harmed.
Wasn't killed, nothing bad.
But he told me about you,
and I just took his story,
used his diary.
Daniel.
Daniel, I'm your friend.
I'm not trying to hurt you.
Never.
Just survive.
No!
Who is it?
I'm Bandy.
Yes. Yes.
William Bandy.
Yeah, I'd like to lease your land.
I had asked for you to come and talk to me before.
When you were leasing land.
That's right, yes.
My boy's been very sick, you know.
This was before your boy got sick.
Now, I know that you would like to build a pipeline
through my property.
- Is that right, what I've heard? - It's absolutely right. And,
well...
Eight inch pipe. It could be buried with your consent.
I guarantee you absolutely no disruption...
God.
God has told me what you must do.
And what is that?
You should be washed in the blood of Jesus Christ.
But I am.
I have been washed, Mr. Bandy. I have been.
It's your only way to salvation. And your only way for what you want.
You can take it at the Church of the Third Revelation.
I'll pay you $3,000.
I'd like you to be part of our church.
I'll pay you $5,000.
Be baptized.
Be forgiven for the sin that you've done.
What sin are you referring to, Mr. Bandy?
My sin of drilling?
I truly wish everyone could be saved, don't you?
Yes.
I am afraid that's just not the case.
The doctrine of universal salvation is a lie, is it not?
- It's a lie. - It's a lie.
I wish everyone could be saved, but they won't. No, they won't.
You will never be saved if you...
Reject the blood.
Good.
Now, is there a sinner here looking for salvation?
A new member?
I'll ask it again.
Is there a sinner here looking for God?
Yes.
Allow me.
Thank you for coming, brother Daniel.
Thank you, Eli.
We have a sinner with us here who wishes for salvation!
- Daniel, are you a sinner? - Yes.
The Lord can't hear you, Daniel.
Say it to him. Go ahead and speak to him. It's all right.
- Yes. - Down on your knees.
Pray to him.
Look up to the sky and say it.
What do you want me to say?
Daniel, you've come here and you've brought good and wealth,
but you have also brought your bad habits as a backslider.
You've lusted after women, and you have abandoned your child.
Your child, that you raised, you have abandoned
all because he was sick and you have sinned.
So say it now. I am a sinner.
- I am a sinner. - Say it louder.
- I am a sinner. - I am a sinner.
Louder, Daniel! I am a sinner!
- I am a sinner. - I am sorry, Lord.
- I am sorry, Lord. - I want the blood.
- I want the blood. - You have abandoned your child.
I have abandoned my child.
- I will never backslide. - I will never backslide.
I was lost, but now I am found.
- I was lost, but now I'm found. - I have abandoned my child.
Say it. Say it.
- I abandoned my child. - Say it louder. Say it louder!
I've abandoned my child!
I've abandoned my boy!
Now beg for the blood!
Just give me the blood, Eli. Let me get out of here.
Give me the blood, Lord, and let me get away!
Do you accept Jesus Christ as your Lord and Savior?
- Yes, I do. - Get out of here, devil!
Out, devil! Out, sin!
- Let me feel the power of the Lord, Eli. - Do you accept
the Church of the Third Revelation as your spiritual guide?
- Get out of here, ghost! - Where is your Lord, Eli?
- Get out! Go back where you belong! - Where is he? There he is!
Do you accept Jesus Christ as your Savior?
Yes, I do.
Would you be free from the burden of sin?
There's power in the blood
Power in the blood
Would you o'er evil a victory win?
There's a pipeline.
There's wonderful power in the blood
There is power, power wonder-working power
In the blood of the Lamb
Praise the Lord!
Welcome to the fold, brother Plainview.
Welcome, brother Daniel. God bless you.
God bless you.
- Hallelujah. - Amen.
Welcome home, brother.
That's enough. That's enough, now.
He must take the spirit in on his own.
We have a new member.
- Yes, brother. - Hallelujah.
- Hallelujah. - Amen.
- My sweet Mary. - Mr. Plainview has been generous
enough to make a $5,000 donation
to the church which we are still waiting for.
That does me good. That does me good.
Welcome home, son.
This here's George Reynolds. Teacher from the deaf school.
- Mr. Plainview. - Fletcher.
You're too heavy for me.
Do you want to get something to eat?
That's the pipeline, see? All the way to the sea.
Come here.
I love you, son.
Let's take a look at you.
All right. That's it, that's it. That's it.
Let's get some decent food inside of you.
That's all we need here is a good, strong, expensive meal.
You hungry?
- Waiter? - Yes, sir.
Two steaks, a whiskey, and water for him.
- And goat's milk. - Very good, sir.
We're going to have this teacher help you.
He's going to help take care of all of this. Understand?
'Cause I need you. Need your help.
Got everything we need now to build this company. Come here.
Good afternoon.
- How are you doing? - It's nice to see you again.
- We need four. - I'll have them right up.
- Good afternoon, Daniel. - Tilford.
Good afternoon.
- Hello! H.M. Tilford! - You don't have to shout.
Pleasure.
It's good to be in Little B.
- Could use some rain out here. - Yeah, we could.
- There we go. - R.J., how's the London broil?
Believe we ordered these drinks before those people.
- R.J., tell us. How's the London broil? - Excuse me, gentlemen. Sorry.
I am sorry about that, sir. I'll have your steaks right out.
- So that green turtle soup is fantastic. - Is it?
lt's delicious.
Sounds good to me.
So Standard offered us a million dollars for the Little Boston leases.
I told H.M. Tilford where he could shove that.
And we made a deal with Union! On the pipeline!
And that whole ocean of oil underneath our fields.
...$150,000. - Yes.
We needed the money to drill.
- Who is this guy? - I go out to meet him.
He's getting oil on the property. We're trying to make a claim on it.
Offered him a million dollars.
- Turned us down flat. - Well, I'm hungry.
Orange fritters, mashed potatoes, green peas.
- All the way around? - All right.
Hold on.
I want you to look over there.
- Daniel, let me introduce... - Look over there. You see?
That's my son. See him?
- Yes. - Do you see?
I see him.
You don't tell me how to raise my family.
I told you not to tell me how to raise my family.
Daniel...
So what do you see?
- I'm very happy for you that the deal... - Yes, I made a deal with Union.
- My son is happy. He's safe. - Congratulations.
- I'm taking care of him now, so... - Excellent.
You look like a fool, don't you, Tilford?
- Yes. - Yes.
Yes, you do.
Excuse me, gentlemen.
Excuse me, gentlemen. Excuse him, gentlemen.
I told you what I was going to do.
My son.
Mr. Sunday, I understand that you're leaving our fair community.
- Yes, I'm going on a mission. - Where you going?
Oildale, Taft, and then on to Bakersfield.
Well, I want you to know...
Three quarters of an hour.
...you done a great job for us.
- Thank you. You will be in my prayers. - I thank you very much.
Union Oil Company, Santa Paula, California.
"The woman saith unto him, 'Sir, give me this water
"'and I shall thirst not, neither come hither to draw."'
Come in, come in.
Can we be alone?
This is my closest associate. He hears everything.
- I'd prefer to speak to you in private. - You can't speak.
So why don't you flap your hands about
and have what's-his-name tell me where you've been.
Or do you think I don't know?
This is hard for me to say.
I'll tell you first, I love you very much.
I've learned to love what I do because of you.
I'm leaving here.
I'm going to Mexico.
I'm taking Mary, and I'm going to Mexico.
I miss working outside.
I miss the fields.
It'll only be for a time,
for me to do my own drilling
and start my own company.
It's time to make a change.
This makes you my competitor.
- No. No, it's not like that. - It is like that, boy.
Your own company, huh?
That's right.
In Mexico?
Yes.
You are making such a misstep. So, what are you doing?
I know you and I have disagreed over many things.
I'd rather keep you as my father than my partner.
Then say it.
If you've got something to say to me, then say it.
I'd like to hear you speak instead of your little dog.
I'm going to Mexico with my wife.
I'm going away from you.
That wasn't so hard, was it?
Killing us with what you're doing.
You're killing my image of you as my son.
You are stubborn. You won't listen.
You're not my son.
Please don't say that. I know you don't mean it.
It's the truth. You're not my son. You never have been.
You're an orphan!
Did you ever hear that word?
Tell him what I said.
You operated here today like one.
I should have seen this coming.
I should have known that, under this all, these past years
you've been building new hate for me, piece by piece.
I don't even know who you are because you have none of me in you.
You're someone else's.
This anger. Your maliciousness.
Backwards dealings with me.
You're an orphan from a basket in the middle of the desert.
And I took you for no other reason than I needed a sweet face to buy land.
Did you get that?
So now you know.
Look at me! You're lower than a bastard.
You have none of me in you. You're just a bastard from a basket.
I thank God I have none of you in me.
Not my son. Just a little piece of competition.
Bastard from a basket.
Bastard from a basket!
You're a bastard from a basket!
Get up, Mr. Daniel.
Mr. Daniel.
Mr. Daniel, you've got a visitor.
Wake up, Mr. Daniel.
Sir?
You can leave us now.
Daniel.
Daniel Plainview, the house is on fire!
Brother Daniel, it's Eli.
Yes, it is. Yes, it is.
I'll make us a drink.
Your home is a miracle.
It's beautiful.
God bless it.
I've been spreading His word far and wide.
Far and wide.
So much travel for Him.
I've been working in radio.
Yes, so much... So much has been happening.
To be here and find you and see you well is wonderful.
And we have a chance to catch up.
No. Thank you so much.
My brother.
Daniel, my brother by marriage.
We're such old friends. So much time.
Things go up, things go down,
but at least the Lord is always around.
We've seen ups and downs, haven't we?
Are things down for you right now, Eli?
No. No.
But I do come with some sad news.
Perhaps you remember Mr. Bandy?
Mr. Bandy has passed on to the Lord.
He lived to be 99 years old, God bless him.
Mr. Bandy has a grandson. Have you met his grandson, William?
William Bandy is one of the finest members we have
at the Church of the Third Revelation.
He's eager to come to Hollywood to be in movies.
He is very good-looking.
- And I do think he will have success. - That's wonderful.
Would you like me to speak with him?
Daniel, I'm asking if you'd like to have business
with the Church of the Third Revelation
in developing this lease on young Bandy's 1,000-acre tract.
I'm offering you to drill
on one of the great undeveloped fields of Little Boston.
- I'd be happy to work with you. - You would?
Yes, yes, of course. That's wonderful.
But there is one condition for this work.
All right.
I'd like you to tell me that you are a false prophet.
I'd like you to tell me that you are, and have been a false prophet.
And that God is a superstition.
But that's a lie.
It's a lie. I cannot say it.
- When can we begin to drill? - Very soon.
How long will it take to bring in the well?
lt shouldn't take long.
I would like a $100,000 signing bonus,
plus the five that is owed to me with interest.
That's only fair.
I am a false prophet, and God is a superstition.
If that's what you believe, then I will say it.
- Say it like you mean it. - Daniel.
Say it like it's your sermon.
Don't smile.
I am a false prophet.
- God is a superstition. - Why don't you stand up?
Put your glass down.
I am a false prophet.
- God is a superstition. - Eli, stop.
Just imagine this is your church here and you have a full congregation, so...
I am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
Say it again.
They can't hear you at the back.
I am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
Say it again.
I am a false prophet! God is a superstition!
Those areas have been drilled.
What?
Those areas, they've been drilled.
- No, they haven't. - Yes, it's...
It's called drainage, Eli.
See, I own everything around it, so, of course, I get what's underneath it.
But there are no derricks there.
This is the Bandy tract. Do you understand?
Do you understand, Eli?
That's more to the point. Do you understand?
I drink your water. I drink it up every day.
I drink the blood of Lamb from Bandy's tract.
You can sit down again.
Daniel.
Please.
- I am in desperate times. - I know.
- I need a friend. - Yes. Of course, you do.
I've sinned.
I need help. I'm a sinner.
I've let the devil grab hold of me in ways I never imagined.
I'm so full of sin.
The Lord sometimes challenges us, doesn't He, Eli?
- Yes, He does, Daniel. - Yes, He does.
Yes, He does!
He's completely failed to alert me to the recent panic in our economy.
- And this... - Oh, dear.
I must have this, Daniel. I must, I must, I must have this.
My investments have...
Daniel, I won't bore you, but if I could grab the Lord's hand for help I would,
but He does these things all the time.
These mysteries that He presents, and while we wait...
While we wait for His word!
Because you're not the chosen brother, Eli.
'Twas Paul who was chosen.
He found me and told me about your land. You're just a fool.
- Why are you talking about Paul? - I did what your brother couldn't.
- Don't say this to me. - I broke you and I beat you.
It was Paul told me about you.
He's the prophet. He's the smart one. He knew what was there
and he found me to take it out of the ground.
Know what the funny thing is? Listen, listen.
I paid him $10,000 cash in hand. Just like that.
He has his own company now. Prosperous little business.
Three wells producing, $5,000 a week.
Stop crying, you sniveling ass. Stop your nonsense.
- You're just the afterbirth, Eli. - No.
That slithered out on your mother's filth.
No.
They should've put you in a glass jar on the mantelpiece.
Where were you when Paul was suckling at his mother's teat?
Where were you?
Who was nursing you, poor Eli? One of Bandy's sows?
That land has been had. Nothing you can do about it. It's gone.
- lf you would just take this lease... - You lose.
Drainage!
Drainage, Eli, you boy.
Drained dry. I'm so sorry.
If you have a milkshake
and I have a milkshake,
and I have a straw, there it is. That's the straw, you see?
Watch it.
Now my straw reaches across the room
and starts to drink your milkshake.
I drink your milkshake!
- I drink it up! - Don't bully me, Daniel.
Did you think your song and dance and your superstition would help you, Eli?
I am the Third Revelation. I am who the Lord has chosen.
- Daniel! - Because I'm smarter than you!
I'm older!
I'm your old friend, Daniel!
- I'm not a false prophet... - Help me! Help me!
...you sniveling boy!
I am the Third Revelation! I am the Third Revelation!
- I told you I would eat you. - We're family!
- I told you I would eat you up! - We're brothers! We're brothers!
Daniel, please forgive me. I beg you.
That's it. That's it.
Mr. Daniel?
I'm finished.